{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "When applied to an entire country, this process is known as an \"interdict,\" which was notably\nused against England under King John. This process was applied to Holy Roman Emperor Henry\nIV, who had to kneel in the snow at Canossa to have it reversed by Pope Gregory VII. For 10\npoints, identify this process of withholding sacraments from a person who has offended Catholic\nlaw.",
      "answer": "excommunication"
    },
    {
      "question": "Albert Gallatin attempted to calm the Mingo Creek Association during this event, which was\nsuppressed by the \"Watermelon Army\" led by Light Horse Harry Lee. Sitting President George\nWashington personally rode out against this event in 1794. For 10 points, name this Western\nPennsylvania uprising against a new excise tax on liquor.",
      "answer": "Whiskey Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting by this man was ordered defaced by the Council of Trent, leading to the man who\naltered his work being known as \"The Breeches-Painter.\" Daniele da Volterra added loincloths to\ncover the nudity in this man's The Last Judgment. For 10 points, name this painter who worked\nlying on his back on a scaffold to decorate the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel.",
      "answer": [
        "Michelangelo",
        "Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni",
        "Buonarroti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An attempt to fly this country's flag at an American school here led to the \"Martyrs' Day\" riot.\nThis country's dictator Omar Torrijos (toh-REE-hoce) signed a treaty with Jimmy Carter that gave\nthis country control over a formerly extraterritorial \"zone.\" For 10 points, name this country which\nthe U.S. encouraged to declare independence from Colombia in order to build a canal.",
      "answer": "Panama"
    },
    {
      "question": "George Taylor opened a mill to produce this good in a way that satisfied Quakers affiliated with\nthe Free Produce Movement. Slaves in tobacco fields dreaded being \"sold down the river\" to work\nwith this good. For 10 points, name this good produced in the Deep South, which became\neconomically feasible again after Eli Whitney invented its \"gin.\"",
      "answer": "cotton"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state was where Teddy Roosevelt once suffered an economic setback as a rancher, though\ntoday it’s the site of Theodore Roosevelt National Park. This state’s economy has recently boomed\ndue to lucrative oil wells around its city of Williston. For 10 points, name this state whose capital\nwas named to attract German immigrants, and which was depicted in the 1990’s film Fargo.",
      "answer": "North Dakota"
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of this decade, the Mayerling scandal erupted. During this decade, Chinese Gordon\nwas killed fighting the Mahdi in Sudan. The rules for colonialism were set out at the Berlin\nConference during this decade. For 10 points, identify this decade in which Queen Victoria\ncelebrated the Golden Jubilee of her 1837 accession to the throne.",
      "answer": [
        "1880s",
        "1880"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man secured recognition of independence at the Treaty of Lausanne, which ended the\ndeportation of his country's Greek minority. This founder of the Republican People's Party banned\nthe wearing of fezzes and introduced the Latin alphabet as part of the \"Six Arrows\" platform. For\n10 points, name this founder of modern secular Turkey.",
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa Kemal",
        "Kemal",
        "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
        "Ataturk"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This author fictionalized Vice-President Aaron Burr in her novel The Minister's Wooing and\ndepicted fugitives in the Great Dismal Swamp in Dred. She wrote a \"key to\" her major novel,\nwhich led Abraham Lincoln to describe her as \"the little lady who started this big war.\" For 10\npoints, name this author who created Simon Legree in the anti-slavery book Uncle Tom's Cabin.",
      "answer": [
        "Harriet Beecher Stowe",
        "Stowe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Cincinnati's George Remus made his fortune in this activity, possibly inspiring the title\ncharacter of The Great Gatsby. An urban legend stating that the Kennedy family originally made\nits fortune in this activity is based on the testimony of Frank Costello, one of many mobsters\ninvolved in it. For 10 points, what was this activity of smuggling alcohol during Prohibition?",
      "answer": [
        "bootlegging",
        "rumrunning"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What city defeated Genoa (in the Chioggia (pr. kee-OH-juh) War and grew into a great\nmaritime power under the leadership of \"doges?\"",
      "answer": "Venice"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state was the home of the \"sage of Emporia,\" Progressive activist William Allen White.\nThis state dropped the teaching of evolution from science classes in 1999. Earlier, this state was\nwhere \"Border Ruffians\" perpetrated the sack of Lawrence and were subject to the Pottawatomie\nMassacre by John Brown. For 10 points, name this state which was \"Bleeding\" in the 1850s.",
        "answer": "Kansas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Wild West town in Kansas was where Bat Masterson and Wyatt Earp served as\nlaw enforcement officers in the 1870’s?",
        "answer": "Dodge City"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Argun and Ussuri rivers demarcate part of the border between these two countries. These\ntwo countries established their border in 1689 with the Treaty of Nerchinsk, which ended a brief\nconflict in the Amur River region. These two countries share a border in between Mongolia and\nKazakhstan. For 10 points, name these two geographically largest countries in Asia.",
        "answer": "Russia and China"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Soviet leader's \"Secret Speech\" denouncing Stalinism was the turning point in the\nSino-Soviet split of the 1950s?",
        "answer": [
          "Nikita Khrushchev",
          "Khrushchev",
          "Nikita Sergeyevich Khrushchev"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this sport, the Hershey Bears have won eleven Calder Cups. In 2014, Metallurg Magnitogorsk\nwon the Gagarin Cup as champion of a prominent European league for this sport. The top league\nin this sport awards the Hart Trophy to its MVP and the Conn Smythe Trophy to the best playoff\nperformer. For 10 points, name this sport whose champion receives the Stanley Cup.",
        "answer": [
          "ice hockey",
          "hockey"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What team, which plays at Nassau Coliseum, won four straight Stanley Cups from 1980\nto 1983?",
        "answer": [
          "New York Islanders",
          "Islanders"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Jopling wrote the standard textbook on this disease. The Greek island of Spinalonga\nonce housed people with this disease, who were treated by Marianne Cope and \"Father Damien\"\non Molokai in Hawaii. For 10 points, name this disease whose causative agent was identified in\n1873 by Gerhard Hansen, and whose sufferers were once isolated into namesake \"colonies.\"",
        "answer": "leprosy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1950, William Jopling established a leprosy hospital named after what body of water\nin the Middle East, in which lepers were instructed to bathe in the Bible?",
        "answer": [
          "Jordan River",
          "Jordan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s government organized the Congress of People’s Deputies and signed the\nIntermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty. He introduced economic restructuring known as\n\"perestroika\" (pr. peh-rez-TROY-kuh) and government transparency called \"glasnost\". For 10\npoints, name this rival of Boris Yeltsin who was the final leader of the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": [
          "Mikhail Gorbachev",
          "Gorbachev",
          "Mikhail Sergeyevich Gorbachev"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gorbachev ended the \"internal exile\" of what dissenting physicist, the inventor of the\nSoviet hydrogen bomb and namesake of a human rights prize?",
        "answer": [
          "Andrei Sakharov",
          "Sakharov",
          "Andrei Dmitrievich Sakharov"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following this battle, Locris and Phocia (pr. FOH-see-uh) \"Medized\" (pr. MEED-eyzd). This\nbattle ended after Ephialtes (pr. eph-FYE-ull-TEEZ) showed the \"goat path\" to the winning\nforce, commanded by Xerxes (pr. ZERK-seez). For 10 points, name this 480 BC battle in which\nLeonidas (pr. LEE-oh-NYE-duss) led three hundred Spartans in holding a pass for three days\nagainst Persia.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Thermopylae",
          "Thermopylae"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Also present at Thermopylae were troops from what city, which used the Sacred Band to\ncome to prominence in the fourth century BC and was the legendary home of Oedipus (pr. ED-uhpuss)?",
        "answer": "Thebes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man collected scrapbooks filled with pictures of Condoleeza Rice, and he once set up a tent\nnear the United Nations where he resided with his \"Amazonian Guard.\" He was killed near Sirte\n(pr. SUR-tay) in October 2011 following his overthrow in the Arab Spring. For 10 points, identify\nthis nemesis of Ronald Reagan who was the forty-year dictator of Libya.",
        "answer": [
          "Muammar Gadaffi",
          "Gadaffi"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Several of Gadaffi's family members were injured by a U.S. bombing raid in 1986\nfollowing the Libyan government's assault on a disco in what city, previously the site of a 1948\n\"airlift?\"",
        "answer": [
          "West Berlin",
          "Berlin"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Bahcall and Raymond Davis searched for these particles in the Homestake experiment.\nThe 1956 experiment of Clyde Cowan and Frederick Reines confirmed their existence. Enrico\nFermi coined the name for these particles, whose \"flavor oscillation\" was a problem of late\ntwentieth-century physics. For 10 points, name these particles with very little mass and no charge.",
        "answer": [
          "neutrinos",
          "neutrino",
          "antineutrinos",
          "antineutrino",
          "solar neutrino",
          "solar neutrinos"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The neutrino was first proposed, though without a name, by what scientist, whose\nconcept of particle spin led him to formulate a namesake \"exclusion principle\" about fermions?",
        "answer": [
          "Wolfgang Pauli",
          "Pauli"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THIRTY YEARS WAR",
      "prompt": "During the Thirty Years War, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Increasingly chaotic German “empire” whose member states took opposing sides?",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Roman Empire",
            "Holy Roman",
            "Hapsburg Empire",
            "Hapsburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Major world religion whose Protestant Reformation was one of the war’s ultimate causes?",
          "answer": "Christianity"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty which formally ended the conflict?",
          "answer": [
            "Peace of Westphalia",
            "Westphalia",
            "Munster",
            "Osnabruck",
            "Treaty of Westphalia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Activity which peaked during the war, and used the Malleus Mallificarum to determine whom to\nburn?",
          "answer": [
            "witch-hunts",
            "witch",
            "witch-hunting"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose pragmatic policy was made by Cardinal Richelieu (pr. ree-shell-OO)?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Event in which two diplomats were thrown out a window that sparked the fighting?",
          "answer": "Defenestration of Prague"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Sweden who was killed at the Battle of Lutzen?",
          "answer": [
            "Gustavus Adolphus",
            "Gustav II",
            "Gustav Adolf"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Watershed historical year in which it ended?",
          "answer": "1648"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE U.K. IN THE 1990’S",
      "prompt": "In the 1990s, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City where the Jubilee underground line on the tube was extended?",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiday shortly before Easter for which a Northern Ireland peace accord was named?",
          "answer": "Good Friday"
        },
        {
          "question": "Labour Party Prime Minister who began his ten-year term in 1997?",
          "answer": [
            "Tony Blair",
            "Blair",
            "Anthony Charles Lynton Blair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose “United” soccer team was managed by Sir Alex Ferguson?",
          "answer": "Manchester"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where a Scottish parliament was established?",
          "answer": "Edinburgh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime Chancellor of the Exchequer who ultimately succeeded to the premiership in 2007?",
          "answer": [
            "Gordon Brown",
            "Brown"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Five-member \"girl group\" whose song \"Wannabe\" led the British pop culture revival?",
          "answer": "The Spice Girls"
        },
        {
          "question": "1992 treaty creating the European Union which Britain joined?",
          "answer": [
            "Maastricht Treaty",
            "Maastricht"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "JOHN QUINCY ADAMS",
      "prompt": "Fun-loving Sixth U.S. President John Quincy Adams...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the first-ever U.S. ambassador to what country, where he presented credentials at St.\nPetersburg?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Both won and lost Presidential elections against what populist Democrat known as “Old\nHickory?”",
          "answer": [
            "Andrew Jackson",
            "Jackson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Secretary of State who composed what statement against European intervention in the\nAmericas?",
          "answer": "Monroe Doctrine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kept which type of dangerous pet reptile, whose range overlaps with crocodiles only in Florida?",
          "answer": "Alligator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elevated what Great Compromiser to Secretary of State after becoming President?",
          "answer": [
            "Henry Clay",
            "Clay"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was known for swimming naked in which river on which Washington DC lies?",
          "answer": "Potomac"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was forced to take on what pro-slavery extremist, who later led the nullification movement, as\nVice-President?",
          "answer": [
            "John C. Calhoun",
            "Calhoun",
            "John Caldwell Calhoun"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Allegedly orchestrated what underhanded plan to win the House ballot in the election of 1824?",
          "answer": "Corrupt Bargain"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A person by this name was the fanatically Catholic Duke of Guise (pr. GHEEZ) while\nanother man of this name was the final king of the Valois (pr. val-WAH) Dynasty. Another\nman of this name was originally the king of (20 pts) ",
        "Navarre and said \"Paris is worth a mass\" to\nexplain his conversion to Catholicism. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, give this name of three men who fought\nthe last French War of Religion, including the first Bourbon king of France."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Henry",
        "Henri"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man died mysteriously at the Grinder's Stand inn in 1809 while journeying on the\nNatchez Trace. In 1804, he departed from St. Louis (20 pts) ",
        "with another man whom he had hired\nfor the Corps of Discovery. Along the way, he met (10 pts) ",
        "Sacajawea and reached the British\nOregon Territory. For 10 points, name this man who was appointed to explore western North\nAmerica by Thomas Jefferson along with William Clark."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Meriwether Lewis",
        "Lewis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) When this phenomenon is enacted to target negative externalities, it is known as\n\"Pigouvian\" (pr. pig-OO-vee-uhn). According to supply-side economics, this process produces\nsimilar (20 pts) ",
        "revenues at the extremes, as demonstrated by the Laffer curve. A slogan in the\nAmerican revolution decried the imposition of this process (10 pts) ",
        "\"without representation.\" For 10\npoints, identify this process in which the government legally compels people to provide money."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "taxation",
        "tax"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During primaries in this Presidential election year, hippies were urged to shave in the\n\"keep clean for Gene\" campaign. A ticket in this election year contained a man who\npromised to \"bomb them back into the (20 pts) ",
        "Stone Age\" and was the last third-party\nPresidential ticket to capture multiple electoral votes. The success of George (10 pts) ",
        "Wallace in\nthis election year inspired the alleged \"Southern Strategy.\" For 10 points, name this year in which\nHubert Humphrey lost to Richard Nixon."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "68",
        "1968"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man led a legion in support of the Colorado Party during the Uruguayan Civil War.\nHe later took command of the Hunters of the Alps to fight against Austria, which challenged\nhis project that included the Siege of (20 pts) ",
        "Gaeta undertaken by the Expedition of the\nThousand. This man allied with Count (10 pts) ",
        "Cavour to achieve the Risorgimento (pr. reeSORGE-ee-MEN-toe). For 10 points, name this general who led the Redshirts on a successful\ncampaign to unify Italy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Giuseppe Garibaldi",
        "Garibaldi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Investigator Leonora Barry advocated for women within this organization. This\norganization was led by a \"Grand Master Workman\" and was an expansion of a\nPhiladelphia-based tailors' union led by (20 pts) ",
        "Uriah Stephens. The Union Pacific strike of 1884\nwas its high-water mark, and it eventually lost influence due to excluding (10 pts) ",
        "unskilled\nworkers and most blacks. For 10 points, name this first large trade union in the U.S., which grew\nunder Terrence Powderley."
      ],
      "answer": "Knights of Labor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The latest date for this facility's destruction is 642, according to the story blaming Amr ibn\nal As, though it is also believed that Theophilus ordered it (20 pts) ",
        "burned in 391 or that it fell\nvictim to the chaos of the Zenobia revolt. This building housed thousands of (10 pts) ",
        "scrolls and\ntablets and was the jewel of a complex dedicated to the Muses by Ptolemy (pr. TAH-luh-mee).\nFor 10 points, name this center of learning in the Classical world, which was found in Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Library of Alexandria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a musical named for this dance, Judge Forestier (pr. for-ess-TEER) finally concludes\nthat \"It's All Right With Me.\" That Cole Porter musical discusses the scandal that this\ndance, which is in 2/4 time and based on the quadrille (pr. kwah-DREEL), caused when it was\nintroduced to (20 pts) ",
        "Paris in 1858. This dance first appeared in Jacques (10 pts) ",
        "Offenbach's Orpheus\nin the Underworld. For 10 points, name this characteristic French music hall dance involving\nwomen kicking their legs high."
      ],
      "answer": "the can-can"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man revised the pamphlet The Falsifiers of History to present his side of 1930s events,\nand he gave the \"Dizzy From Success\" speech to explain why he was modifying goals of the (20 pts) ",
        "First Five-Year Plan. This leader orchestrated the \"show trials\" of army generals and\nothers, decimating his military before the (10 pts) ",
        "Nazi invasion of his country in Operation\nBarbarossa. For 10 points, name this fan of gulags who was the dictator of the Soviet Union from\n1924 to 1953."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Joseph Stalin",
        "Ioseb Besarionis Dze Jugashvili",
        "Jugashvili"
      ]
    }
  ]
}